<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Tools | tombola]]></title>
  <link href="http://tombola.github.io/blog/categories/tools/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://tombola.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-22T15:32:04+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://tombola.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Tom Readings]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Prezi Desktop]]></title>
    <link href="http://tombola.github.io/blog/2014/03/21/Prezi-Desktop/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://tombola.github.io/blog/2014/03/21/Prezi-Desktop</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The implied excitement above is slightly disingenuous. Prezi is a familiar tool to most people working in education by now, but also the cause of frequent (literal) headaches, and thus not a drop in replacement for powerpoint (unlike google presentations, but that is another post)</p>

<p><a href="http://prezi.com/ubiqmwfo9dnp/dizzy/"><img src="/images/prezi_screenshot.png" alt="prezi example" /></a></p>

<!--<iframe src="http://prezi.com/embed/ubiqmwfo9dnp/?bgcolor=ffffff&amp;lock_to_path=1&amp;autoplay=0&amp;autohide_ctrls=0&amp;features=undefined&amp;disabled_features=undefined" width="700" height="350" frameBorder="0" webkitAllowFullScreen="1" mozAllowFullscreen="1" allowfullscreen="1"></iframe>&#8211;>


<p>Anyway, Prezi has its uses, and some academics/students find it can help them liven up an otherwise static presentation (when used carefully/sparingly).</p>

<p>I was recently notified that I had a free trial of the Prezi pro, which includes access to the desktop app recently, so I thought I would test it out.</p>

<p>Main differences between desktop and web version:</p>

<ul>
<li>you can work offline</li>
<li>performance when dragging things about or using images is a little snappier</li>
</ul>


<p>There really is little else. You can already <a href="https://prezi.zendesk.com/entries/22441718-download-a-portable-prezi">download a copy of your prezi</a> from the web version of Prezi to use offline (no software required), so that is not a distinguishing feature. The app interface (sensibly) is exactly the same as the online experience</p>

<p>For a free education account, which already has the ability to get rid of the prezi logo, and allows private presentations, the only advantages of Prezi Edu Pro (~$5/month) are extra storage (2gb rather than 500mb), and the desktop app*.</p>

<h3>Verdict</h3>

<p>The pro account (with desktop app) is a handy thing to have, if:</p>

<ul>
<li>you like using prezi to get your point across</li>
<li>you are blighted by a slow internet connection</li>
<li>you are a heavy user of prezi</li>
<li>you would like to make/amend your presentation on the train</li>
</ul>


<p>It might not be worth paying for the Edu Pro account if:</p>

<ul>
<li>you work in education (and have the free edu account)</li>
<li>you have decent and reliable internet connection</li>
<li>you do not travel by train (much)</li>
</ul>


<p>Also worth considering is <strong>whether to use Prezi at all</strong>, but that mainly comes down to how easy you find it to use, what your content is, and your audience. I would say, with a high degree of bias - if you are a fan of stock imagery do not use Prezi (because in all likelihood you are also a headspinning prezi fan..)</p>

<hr />

<p>* <em>There is &lsquo;premium support&rsquo; as well, but to be honest, if the online help resources are not up to scratch there is no point in engaging with a tool like this, which should hopefully be simple to use anyway.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
