<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Thoughts | tombola]]></title>
  <link href="http://localhost:4000//blog/categories/thoughts/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://localhost:4000//"/>
  <updated>2014-09-12T10:08:07+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://localhost:4000//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Tom Readings]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What Are Computers For?]]></title>
    <link href="http://localhost:4000//blog/2014/03/26/What-are-computers-for/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-26T16:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://localhost:4000//blog/2014/03/26/What-are-computers-for</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--<div class="alert alert-info">I tend to use the word &#8216;technology&#8217; liberally, but I am almost always referring to computerised systems, and in the main those that make use of the world wide web.</div>&#8211;>




<p class="lead"> The actual computer is lost in the background somewhat since we started talking in terms of <em>apps</em>, <em>tools</em>, <em>systems</em> etc, making an implicit assumption that the information processing underneath just happened. Also, adding to the confusion, we don&#8217;t even call some &#8216;devices&#8217; computers anymore (eg portable devices).</p>


<p>It is easy to get seduced by, and caught up in a continual cycle of interaction with  &lsquo;information technologies&rsquo;. I often feel that I am slowly losing contact with what the initial purpose of these complicated systems, and that feeding and caring for them as informational entities becomes the goal itself, either for myself or others.</p>

<p>The application of computers gets more and more complex and subtle, but still (at the time of writing), computers are really good at some stuff, and really bad at others:</p>

<div class="well">
<ol>
<li>Computers are good at storing, processing and distributing unambiguous information</li>
<br>

<li>Computers are really, really bad at making sense or meaning out of the information*</li>
</ol>
</div>


<p>Therefore in order for an informational transaction to have value, <em>technologies</em> need to receive information from us or our environment, perform some sort of calculation, and then <strong>deliver it to us</strong>. Hopefully, on the way, the technology will have added value via 1), and not lost fidelity by attempting to encroach too far into 2) (think automated stock market crash).</p>

<p>I make contact with an information transaction via an <em>interface</em>, which is provided to me by the computer as a compromise. This facilitates the transformation of my wooly, myopic, emotionally tinted thinking into crystalline, unambiguous commands, and vice versa.</p>

<p>There is a potential information cost in each of these transactions. In the early days the conversation with the computer might compare to a slow debate via post with a Polish guy in Chinese. Nowadays it might approach a shouted conversation in a bar with a socially inept stranger.</p>

<p>I think it is still worth stepping back and checking that for any one use of technology the information transactions required are not so <strong>costly</strong> that they outweighs the <strong>benefits</strong> (of storage, processing or distribution). We are, after all, still in the mass-cultural early days of our relationship with computers.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll admit that I don&rsquo;t really have a concluding point in this post, I am just restating my personal relationship with technology as a cathartic act and delivering my thoughts for storage - as a linear string of alphanumeric characters.</p>

<hr />

<p>* <em>I should qualify this statement. I realise that a weather prediction cluster can form a complex meteorological model, but it must do this via millions of simple calculations, and it will still not be able to tell if a cloud looks like an elephant.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
